<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | FS</title>
    <link>https://frankschae.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://frankschae.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Frank Schäfer</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 17:26:49 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://frankschae.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://frankschae.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Performance Bounds for Quantum Control</title>
      <link>https://frankschae.github.io/project/controlbounds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 17:26:49 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://frankschae.github.io/project/controlbounds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Control of devices at the quantum level holds enormous potential for current and future applications in the field of quantum information science. However, due to the nonlinear and stochastic nature of quantum systems under continuous observation, analytical solutions to all but the simplest quantum control problems remain unknown. In this project, we present a convex optimization framework to compute informative bounds on the best attainable control performance. Since our approach provides an under-approximator for the value function, we can use it directly to construct near-optimal heuristic controllers as demonstrated for a qubit subjected to homodyne detection and photon counting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Control of (Stochastic) Quantum Dynamics with Differentiable Programming</title>
      <link>https://frankschae.github.io/project/dp_for_control/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:20:29 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://frankschae.github.io/project/dp_for_control/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Conceptually, it is straightforward to determine the time evolution of a quantum system for a fixed initial state given its (time-dependent) Hamiltonian or Lindbladian. Depending on the physical context, the dynamics is described by an ordinary or stochastic differential equation. In quantum state control, which is of paramount importance for quantum computation, we aim at solving the inverse problem. That is, starting from a distribution of initial states, we seek protocols that allow us to reach a desired target state by optimization of free parameters of the differential equation (control drives) in a certain time interval. To solve this control problem, we implement the system dynamics as part of a fully differentiable program and use a loss function that quantifies the distance from the target state. Specifically, we employ a neural network that maps an observation of the state of the qubit to a control drive defined via the differential equation for each time interval. To implement efficient training, we backpropagate the gradient information from the loss function through the SDE solver using adjoint sensitivity methods. Such a procedure should ultimately combine powerful tools from machine learning and scientific computation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning for Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://frankschae.github.io/project/ml_for_pt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 23:56:43 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://frankschae.github.io/project/ml_for_pt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Artificial neural networks have successfully been used to identify phase transitions from data and classify data into distinct phases in an automated fashion. The power and success of these approaches (e.g., &amp;ldquo;learning by confusion&amp;rdquo; or the &amp;ldquo;prediction-based method&amp;rdquo;) can be attributed to the ability of deep neural networks to learn arbitrary functions. However, the larger a neural network, the more computational resources are needed to train it, and the more difficult it is to understand its decision making. In this project, we establish a solid theoretical foundation of popular machine-learning methods that rely on neural networks for detecting phase transitions and develop new efficient numerical routines to identify phase transitions directly from data. In the future, our methods could make it possible to detect as yet unknown phase transitions, for instance in quantum simulators or in novel materials.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Structure and Many-Body Dynamics of Ultracold Bosons in a Double Well </title>
      <link>https://frankschae.github.io/project/mbdynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 10:39:11 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://frankschae.github.io/project/mbdynamics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We examine the spectral structure and many-body dynamics of two and three repulsively interacting bosons trapped in a one-dimensional double-well, for variable barrier height, inter-particle interaction strength, and initial conditions. By exact diagonalization of the many-particle Hamiltonian, we specifically explore the dynamical behavior of the particles launched either at the single-particle ground state or saddle-point energy, in a time-independent potential. We complement these results by a characterization of the cross-over from diabatic to quasi-adiabatic evolution under finite-time switching of the potential barrier, via the associated time evolution of a single particle’s von Neumann entropy. This is achieved with the help of the multiconfigurational time-dependent Hartree method for indistinguishable particles (MCTDH-X)—which also allows us to extrapolate our results for increasing particle numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative Scattering of Scalar Waves by Optimized Configurations of Point Scatterers</title>
      <link>https://frankschae.github.io/project/scattering/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://frankschae.github.io/project/scattering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We investigate multiple scattering of scalar waves by an ensemble of N resonant point scatterers in three dimensions. For up to N = 21 scatterers, we numerically optimize the positions of the individual scatterers, to maximize the total scattering cross section for an incoming plane wave, on the one hand, and to minimize the decay rate associated to a long-lived scattering resonance, on the other. In both cases, the optimum is achieved by configurations where all scatterers are placed on a line parallel to the direction of the incoming plane wave. The associated maximal scattering cross section increases quadratically with the number of scatterers for large N, whereas the minimal decay rate—which is realized by configurations that are not the same as those that maximize the scattering cross section—decreases exponentially as a function of N. Finally, we also analyze the stability of our optimized configurations with respect to small random displacements of the scatterers. These results demonstrate that optimized configurations of scatterers bear a considerable potential for applications such as quantum memories or mirrors consisting of only a few atoms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
